Preliminary Inventory to the Stefan Korbonski papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Stefan Korbonski papers
1943-1983
83065
Hoover Institution Archives
62 manuscript boxes, 6 oversize boxes (29.3 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, dispatches, minutes, bulletins, memoranda, printed matter, phonotapes, and photographs, relating to the underground movement in Poland during World War II, Polish émigré affairs, and the Assembly of Captive European Nations and other anti-communist movements.
Korbonski, Stefan
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Biographical note
Polish underground leader during World War II; subsequently chairman, Assembly of Captive European Nations.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1983.
Scope and Contents note
Speeches and writings, correspondence, dispatches, minutes, bulletins, memoranda, printed matter, phonotapes, and photographs, relating to the underground movement in Poland during World War II, Polish émigré affairs, and the Assembly of Captive European Nations and other anti-communist movements.
ACEN (Organization); Anti-communist movements.; Communism.; Phonotapes.; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945.; Poland.; Poles in foreign countries.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements.; World War, 1939-1945.
- WARTIME UNDERGROUND
  - 1. Original manuscript of W Imieniu Rzeczypospolite j /Fighting Warsaw/ in Polish prepared already in underground /, 1939-1945/ (Box 1-2)
  - 2. Dispatches sent to London in microfilm and others in item 1/two metal boxes/.
  - 3. General Tadeusz Bor-Komorowski's letters mostly handwritten and my replies. /Contents of these letters described in my letter to Hoover Institution of, June 16, 1983/.
  - 4. Research material for my book The Polish Underground State - A Guide to the Underground 1939-1945/1 volume and several large manila envelopes.
  - 5. Show trials in Poland connected with my underground activities and escape/press clippings from the Polish communist newspapers. (Box 3)
  - 6. Original underground files of the Directorate of Civil Resistance smuggled from Poland to the U.S. two volumes, several hundred pages. /See my letter of June 16, 1983/.
  - 7. Moscow Prawda of with extensive coverage of the show trial of 16 top leaders of the Polish wartime underground state., June 20, 1945
- EMIGRATION
  - 1. Free Europe Committee and Radio Free Europe/four volumes (Box 4)
  - 2. European Movement, Central and Eastern European Section /Chairman Harold Macmillan/
  - 3. Central and Eastern European Commission /Chairman Major Edward Beddington-Behrens/
  - 4. Consultative Assembly /Chairman Paul Henri Spaak/Items 2,3,4, together comprise three envelopes (Box 5)
  - 5. Dr.Joseph Retinger - Polish-British emissary to the Polish underground - my article in Polish.
  - 6. United Committees and Councils in exile /Headquarters in New York/one volume
  - 7. International Peasant Union
  - 8. Polish Peasant Party /President Stanislaw Mikolajczyk/Items 7 & 8 comprise 8 volumes, over one thousand pages. (Box 6-18, 67)
  - 9. Assembly of Captive European Nations /ACEN/ a dozen volumes, several thousand pages
  - 10. ACEN NEWS and other ACEN publications - periodical ACEN NEWS from, July-August 1965 to July-August 1968
  - 11. Journal of a trip to South America/large brochure
  - 12. Journal of a trip around the world/large brochure
  - 13. Polska Rada Polityczna, Brzedstawicielstwo w Stanach Zjednoczonych /Polish Political Council, Representation in the U.S./one volume (Box 19-20)
  - 14. Zjednoczenie Narodowe /National Unity/three volumes and six manila envelopes
  - 15. Twentieth Anniversary of the Warsaw Uprising of /two volumes, one carton, 1944 (Box 21-24)
  - 16. Polish Millenium/one volume, one carton.
  - 17. Clippings of over 140 of my letters printed in the American and Western press and dealing with Polish affairs (Box 25)
  - 18. Reviews of my five books - in English and in Polish/several album
  - 19. Cuba - aftermath of invasion/one envelope
  - 20. China -Peking, memo Golden Dragon and White Eagle - two volumes concerning Chinese policy vis-a-vis Poland (Box 26)
  - 21. My thirty years correspondence including letters of prominent Polis personalities/six volumes (Box 27-28)
  - 22. Handwritten manuscript of my additional four books in Polish - one carton /this is in addition to wartime underground item 1, above (Box 29-30)
  - 23. Clippings from the American press concerning my political activities, as well as from Polish and communist press/seven large menila envelopes (Box 31-32)
  - 24. My articles in English and in Polish, speeches, radio broadcasts, reviews and television shows/six volumes and several large manila envelopes (Box 33-37)
  - 25. Collection of books on Polish and European undergrounds
  - 26. Monthly KULTURA published in France in Polish several hundred copies covering about 30 years
  - 27. Tape recordings of my speeches (Box 38-39)
  - 28. Various photographs and albums of historic value (Box 40-41)
  - 29. Personal documents, several portfolios
  - 30. Polonica - two volumes concerning Polish-American Congress and World Polonia Council (Box 42-44)
  - 31. Polska Rada Jednoci w Stanach Zjednoczonych /Polish Council of Unity in the United States/one volume (Box 45-46, 68)
  - 32. Holocaust/two volumes, several manila envelopes
  - 33. International agreements and pledges concerning East-Central Europe/one large brochure (Box 47)
  - 34. International Rescue Committee/one file
  - 35. Polish-Canadian Congress/one volume
  - 36. Polish Institute of Arts and Sciences/one volume
  - 37. Catholic Church/one volume
  - 38. Commission on European Security and Cooperation/two volumes, one envelope (Box 48)
  - 39. Congressional Record /some clippings connected with East European affairs/ (Box 49)
  - 40. The true story of ENIGMA/one volume (Box 50-51)
  - 41. Menachem Begin/one volume
  - 42. Brochures with information furnished by important defectors
  - 43. Crime at Katyn/two volumes (Box 52)
  - 44. Poles in Soviet Russia/one volume
  - 45. Defection of Professor Marek Korowicz with my aid from the Polish communist delegation to the United Nations /clippings, 1953 (Box 53, 68)
  - 46. My testimony at Nuremberg Trial involving German war criminals/one file
  - 47. Letter concerning the destruction of the monument to American fliers at the Cemetery in Lwow
  - 48. Ambassador Bliss Lane/one file
  - 49. Ukrainian affairs/one file
  - 50. Original letters of famous Polish painter, Rafal Malczewski (Box 54)
  - 51. Polish Parliament /Sejm/ in /one file, 1947
  - 52. Marshall Plan for Poland/one file
  - 53. Controversy concerning the plan to transfer the remnants of the late General Sikorski to Poland/one file
  - 54. Paderewski's heart/envelope
  - 55. The last Polish prewar Generals: Abraham and Boruta-Spiechowicz/one envelope
  - 56. My postwar exchange of letters with the Chief of German wartime intelligence, General Reinhard Gehlen, concerning Polish Underground
  - 57. Correspondence with the Chancelery of General Charles de Gaulle
  - 58. The visit of Edward Gierek, first secretary of the Polish Communist party in Washington/clippings
  - 59. Memorial album published in number 1012/ on the occasion of unveiling the monuments to Thaddeus Kosciuszko and Casimir Pulaski in Washington, D.C. Collectors item/, 1911 / May 1910 /
  - 60. Collection of 37 issues of the chief organ of Solidarity in Poland, the weekly Tygodnik Solidarno /Solidarity Weekly/. Best source of information for historians.
- NOTE to Emigration section:
  - Items 7 and 8 supplement the archives of Stanislaw Mikolajczyk already deposited at Hoover Institution.
  - Items 6,9,10,11 and 12 illustrate the activities of political exiles from Albania, Bulgaria, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Estonia, Lithuania, Latvia, Poland and Romania.
  - Items 1,2,3,4 pertain to the aid given to exile organizations by the governments and peoples of the U.S. and Western Europe.
  - Items 13,14,15,16 and 31 are related to the activities of the Polis political emigration.
- SUPPLEMENT
  - 61. Three articles published about me in and some old press clippings concerning my activities., 1982/3 (Box 55)
  - 62. The diploma of the Medal of Honour conferred upon me by Yad Vashem Martyrs' and Heroes' Remembrance Authority in Jerusalem for saving Jews in Nazi occupied Poland in and some press clippings connected with this event., 1939-1945
  - 63. Awards given to me by The Alfred Jurzykowski Foundation, by Underground Home Army Soldiers in Los Angeles and by Perspectives, Inc..
  - 64. Obituary notice in Warsaw designated to the 30th anniversary of the Warsaw Uprising and a copy of GAZETA LUDOWA in Warsaw of concerning the third anniversary of the Warsaw Uprising., August 1, 1947
  - 65. My six books in Polish /W Imieniu Rzeczypospolitej, W Imieniu Kremla, W Imieniu Polski Walczacej, Miedzy mlotem a kowadlem Polskie Pastwo Podziemne - przewodnik po podziemiu z lat 1939-1945, Za murami Kremla - the last published in and my five books in English / Fighting Warsaw, Warsaw in Chains, Warsaw in Exile, Between the Hammer and the Anvil The Polish Underground State - a Guide to the Underground of 1939-1945/., November, 1983/
  - 66. 9 volumes of correspondence and other materials pertaining to point 65. (Box 56-58)
- INCREMENTAL MATERIALS (Box 59-66)